[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
5 Usually, at the morning ritual when the family members told their dreams, Jonas
didn't contribute much. He rarely dreamed. Sometimes he awoke with a
feeling of fragments of float in his sleep, but he couldn't seem to grasp them
and put them together into something worthy of telling at the
ritual this morning was different. He had dreamed very vividly the night
before. His mind wandered while Lily, as usual, recounted a lengthy dream, this one
a frightening one in which she had, against the rules, been riding her
mother's bicycle and been caught by the Security Guards. They all listened carefully and
discussed with Lily the warning that the dream had given.
"Thank you for your dream, Lily." Jonas said the standard phrase automatically, and
tried to pay better attention while his mother told of a dream fragment, a
disquieting scene where she had been chastised for a rule infraction she
didn't understand. Together they agreed that it probably resulted from her
feelings when she had reluctantly dealt punishment to the citizen who had broken
the major rules a second time. Father said that he had had no
dreams. "Gabe?" Father asked, looking down at the basket where the new child lay
gurgling after his feeding, ready to be taken back to the Nurturing Center for the
day. They all laughed dream telling began with Threes. If new children dreamed, no
one knew. "Jonas?" Mother asked. They always asked, though they knew how rarely Jonas
had a dream to tell. "I did dream last night," Jonas told
him He shifted in his chair, frowning.
"Good," Father said. "Tell us." "The details aren't clear, really," Jonas
explained, trying to recreate the odd dream in his mind. "I think I was in the bathing room
at the House of the Old." "That's where you were yesterday," Father pointed
out. Jonas nodded. "But it wasn't really the same. There was a tub, in the dream.
But only one. And the real bathing room has rows and rows of them. But the room
in the dream was warm and damp.
And I had taken off my tunic, but hadn't
put on the smok so my chest was bare. I was perspiring, because it was so
warm. And Fiona was there, the way she was yesterday." "Asher, too?" Mother
asked Jonah shook his head. "No. It was only me and Fiona, alone
in the room, standing beside the tub. She was laughing. But I wasn't. I was
almost a little angry at her, in the dream dream, because she wasn't taking me
seriously." "Seriously about what?" Lily asked. Jonas looked at his plate. For some
reason that he didn't understand, he felt slightly embarrassed. "I think I was
trying to convince her that she should get into the tub of
water." He paused. He knew he had to tell it all, that it was not only all right
but necessary to tell all of a dream. So he forced himself to relate the part
that made him uneasy. "I wanted her to take off her clothes and get into the tub," he
explained quickly. "I wanted to bathe her. I had the sponge in my hand. But she wouldn't. She
kept laughing and saying no." He looked up at his parents. "That's all," he
said. "Can you describe the strongest feeling in your dream, son?" Father asked.
Jonas thought about it. The details were murky and vague the feelings were clear,
and flooded him again now as he thought. "The wanting, he
said. "I knew that she wouldn't. And I think I knew that she shouldn't. But I
wanted it so terribly. I could feel the wanting all through me." "Thank you for
your dream, Jonas," Mother said after a moment. She glanced at
Father. "Lily," Father said, "it's time to leave for school. Would you walk beside
me this morning and keep an eye on the new child's basket? We want to be certain
he doesn't wiggle himself loose." Jonas began to rise to collect his
school books He thought it surprising that they hadn't talked about his dream
at length before the thank you. Perhaps they found it as confusing as he had.
"Wait, Jonas," Mother said gently. "I'll write an apology to your instructor so that
you don't have to speak one for being late." He sank back down into his chair, puzzled.
He waved to Father and Lily as they left the dwelling, carrying Gabe in his
basket. He watched while Mother tidied the remains of the morning meal and
placed the tray by the front door for the Collection Crew. Finally she sat down beside him at
the table. "Jonas," she said with a smile, "the feeling you described as the wanting? It
was your first Stirrings. Father and I have been expecting it to happen to you. It happens
to everyone. It happened to Father when he was your age. And it happened to me. It
will happen someday to Lily very often," Mother added, "it begins with a dream."
Stirrings. He had heard the word before.
He remembered that there was a reference to the Stirrings in the Book of Rules,
though he didn't remember what it said. And now and then the Speaker mentioned
it. ATTENTION. A REMINDER THAT STIRRINGS MUST BE REPORTED IN ORDER FOR TREATMENT
TO TAKE take PLACE. He had always ignored that announcement because he didn't
understand it and it had never seemed to apply to him in any
way. He ignored, as most citizens did, many of the commands and reminders read by
the Speaker. "Do I have to report it?" he asked his mother. She laughed. "You did, in
the dreamt telling That's enough." "But what about the treatment? The Speaker
says the treatment must take place." Jonas felt miserable. Just when the Ceremony
was about to happen happened his Ceremony of 12 would he have to go away
someplace for treatment? Just because of a stupid dream? But his mother laughed again in a
reassuring, affectionate way. "No, no," she said. "It's just the pills. You're ready
for the pills, that's all. That's the treatment for Stirrings." Jonas brightened. He knew about
the pills. His parents both took them each morning. And some of his friends did, he
knew. Once he had been heading off to school with both of them on their bikes,
when Asher's father had called from their dwelling doorway, "You forgot your pill,
Asher!" Asher had groan good-naturedly, turned his bike, and ridden back while Jonas
waited. It was a sort of thing one didn't ask a friend about because it might have
fallen into that uncomfortable category of "being different." Asher took a pill each morning;
Jonas did not. Always better, less rude, to talk about things that were the
same now Now he swallowed the small pill that his mother handed him. "That's all?" he
asked. "That's all," she replied, returning the bottle to the cupboard. "But you
mustn't forget. I'll remind you for the first weeks, but then you must do it on
your own. If you forget, the Stirrings will come back. The dreams of Stirrings
will come back. Sometimes the dosage must be adjusted." "Asher takes them," Jonas confided.
His mother nodded, unsurprised. "Many of your groupmates probably do.
The males, at least. And they all will, soon. Females
too." "How long will I have to take them?"
"Until you enter the House of the Old," she explained. "All of your adult life. But it
becomes routine; after a while you won't even pay much attention to it." She looked
at her watch. "If you leave right now, you won't even be late for school. Hurry
along. "And thank you again, Jonas," she added, as he went to the door, "for your dream."
Pedaling rapidly down the path, Jonas felt oddly proud to have joined those
who took the pills. For a moment, though, he remembered the dream again. The dream had felt
pleasurable. Though the feelings were confused, he thought that he had liked
the feelings that his mother had called Stirrings. He remembered that upon waking,
he had wanted to feel the Stirrings again. Then, in the same way that his own
dwelling slipped away behind him as he rounded a corner on his bicycle, the
dream slipped away from his thoughts.
Very briefly, a little guiltily, he tried to grasp it back. But the feelings had
disappeared. The Stirrings were gone
[Music]